Earlier I mentioned the concept of leased lines, which are dedicated lines a customer can obtain for high-speed, or relatively high-speed, connections.
The first leased line we are going to cover is that of a T1 line.
A full T1 line uses twenty-four 64 Kbps channels of data, plus another 8 Kbps for overhead, for a grand total of 1.544 Mbps.
This is not fast by today's standards, but a T1 line is a dedicated leased line, so whoever leases the line has the full, consistent bandwidth of that line.
Customers that do not want to pay for a full T1 line can lease a partial T1 line, which really means that the customer is not leasing the full allotment of 24 channels.
Of course, the speed won't be as high, either. For customers who do not feel that a T1 line is sufficient, a T3 line can be obtained.
T3 lines run at 44.736 Mbps, which is the equivalent of twenty-eight T1 lines. Technically, T3 lines use six hundred seventy-two 64 Kbps channels.
As with a T1 line, a customer can lease a partial T3 line and pay accordingly. The European equivalent of the T1 and T3 lines are E1 and E3.
The concepts are the same but the number of channels each line uses is different, thus making the line speeds different.
E1 is the European version of the T1 line. It uses thirty-two 64 Kbps channels, so it runs at 2.048 Mbps.
E3 is the European version of the T3 line. It uses the equivalent of sixteen E1 lines, so the speed is 34.368 Mbps, slower than a T3 line even though the E1 line is faster than a T1 line.
For the exam, know that the speeds, in order from slowest to fastest, are T1, E1, E3, and T3.